# 走嘛
Go
# 凉糕哟
Lianggao
# 凉糕诶
# 卖凉糕了
Who wants Lianggao
# 凉糕
Lianggao
# 让它浪起来
Make it swirl
# 今天我跟一个老师父出来体验一下
Today I follow an old master and see
# 挑着担子卖凉糕是什么感觉
what it is like to hawk Lianggao in the street.
# 这个你请的啊
He's your employee?
# 嗯 我是学徒
Umm. I'm an apprentice.
# 当真的啊
You are serious?
# 真的啊 真的 跟师父学哈
Yes. I am. I'm learning from my master.
# 一个当了几年兵的（回来）看到何师傅卖凉糕
A veteran saw Master He selling Lianggao the other day
# 追起追起的要（吃）
He chased him eagerly (for Lianggao)
# 我小时候都追过
Sounds like me when I was little
# 我没有乱说嘛
See? I didn't brag.
# 人家跑到上面拿着多大的碗 噗噗噗地跟都追
He ran a long way to fetch a large bowl and chased him
# 是 我还多久没吃到他的凉糕了
It for sure has been a long time since I last bought Lianggao from him
# 遮都它就是 拉开来一哈遮都就是
Just cover it. Stretch it and put over the basket.
# 凉糕诶 凉糕
Lianggao. Lianggao.
# 凉糕哦
Lianggao.
# 卖凉糕哦 凉糕
Lianggao for sale. Lianggao.
# 你打嘛
Give it a try
# 看你打得来不
See whether you can serve it well
# 这儿给它翻起来
Scoop from the bottom
# 3碗啊
You want three servings, right?
# 嗯
Yes
# 先给你打了来
I'll fetch them
# 凉糕哦
Lianggao
# 打不打（凉糕）
Do you want some (Lianggao)?
# 我不晓得他打不打
I'm not sure whether he wants it
# 我喊了他的
He didn't answer
# 凉糕哦
Lianggao
# 来给我打一碗
Here. I want a bowl (of Lianggao).
# 多点嘛少点
How much (syrup)?
# 跟他舀3勺嘛
3 spoons
# 我先休息一下
I need a rest
# 你还没学会 你挑着就很累
You are tired because you haven't learned the trick
# 是
Indeed
# 凉糕哦
Lianggao
# 现在我们卖得还剩最后三碗
We have 3 bowls of Lianggao left
# 然后这个大姐又要一两碗
And this Sis wanted some
# 好多钱一碗
How much is it?
# 没得了只有三碗 你端一碗去嘛
Only three bowl are left. Come and get one.
# 我给那个小乖乖买一碗去
I will buy one for my little one.
# 好多钱一碗嘛
How much?
# 2元
2 Yuan
# 我这一哈拿钱
Let me get some money
# 没想到还不够卖 真的
I didn't expect that. It's too popular and quickly sold
# 再多来几碗都没问题
We can definitely sell more
# 现在我师父卖完了马上回去现拷（做）
Now my master is going back to make more
# 拷（做）了之后明天又可以接着卖
Get ready for tomorrow's sale
# 因为做出来的不是马上可以吃 要等它冷
Lianggao can't be served right after cooking. It must be cold
# 这哈我整（挑）它得动了
Now I'm able to take it
# 这下可以把它整的动了
Take it easily
# 现在轻了好多 少了几十斤
It is quite lighter now. Dozens of kilos are gone
# 要不要烧火安
Should I light up the fire now?
# 不 要等会
No. Wait a second.
# 这个拷（做）都还要注意到安全
Be careful when making this
# 一烫到你的话甩不脱
It's very hot and sticky. You can't get rid of it if you touch it.
# 好烫啊
How hot?
# 烫来要起泡
Skin-swelling hot
# 你不烧它 它就不得下沉
Heat will make it precipitate
# 全是白色的（沉淀物）
All those white (precipitations)?
# 要烧开之后才会有这个噶
It only forms after boiling
# 先看着没有烧的时候好脏哦噶
It looks quite muddy before boiling
# 嗯 这下多清亮
En. Now it's clear.
# 我先尝一下这个水
Let me have a taste of this solution
# 这哈快当 一会就拷好了
The fire is catching up. It won't take too long.
# 嗯 很强的那个皮蛋（碱）的味道
Um. Very strong century egg (alkaline) taste.
# 那个自贡的还不是啊 专门下来（学）
We had people from Zigong who came all the way just to learn this
# 看了之后回去拷 结果又叫他上去教
He had learned well and taught others
# 这剩下的就是颗粒 你用手去摸嘛
Those are the particles left. You can feel it.
# 哦 颗粒 这是没有被充分打碎的
Oh. Particles that survive the grinding.
# 你没得颗粒就全部都要的
They must be left out
# 我的小孩他看都不得来看一眼 他不学
My kid doesn't ever cast a glance at this. He doesn't want to learn.
# 他不喜欢这个手艺噶
He doesn't like this craft
# 嗯他不得学
No. He doesn't.
# 这个就不加了嘛
We don't need this?
# 要
We do.
# 这个还要加进去啊
Oh, we need this?
# 这个看黏稠度 不够就加点来又拷（做）
We can add some depending on the stickiness
# 哦 还可以后面慢慢的加
Oh. So we can add it later.
# 你看嘛 他慢慢的加
See? He is adding little by little.
# 来 我给你拷都
Here. I'll stir.
# 我来 搅给你看
Give me that. Let me show you how it's done.
# 就是下去那哈就要好好得拷
Stir well once you added that
# 要让它浪起来
Make it swirl
# 这个咋子晓得它的浓稠度呢
How to know how thick it is?
# 这个只有自己掌握老嫩
You have to tell if it's tender or firm from your experience
# 这没满就给它加点
Add it to full
# 小心端哦 慢点烫得很哦
Careful. It's very hot.
# 端一个就可以了 你没端习惯
Just get that one. You need more practice.
# 锅巴呀
Crispy rice!
# 就像以前做的浑水粑味道
It tastes like Hun Shui Ba (another rice made food)
# 嗯 很香这个
Um. Taste good.
# 就是这个浆浆好吃 你夹一点来试试嘛
This chunky stuff is good. Try it.
# 我女儿就喜欢吃这个
My daughter likes it
# 绵绵的
Very soft
# 有浑水粑的味道
Taste like Hun Shui Ba
# 我们这刚好66碗
We have 66 bowls here
# 现在煮了一大锅就做了66碗
We made 66 bowls from that batch
# 大概是四五斤 四斤左右的大米
We used about 4 Jin (2kg) rice
# 现在又学会一样传统手艺了
Now I learned a new traditional craft
# 过两天拍个视频
I'll make a video about it in a couple of days
# 66碗 刚好66碗
Exactly 66 bowls
# 64 那儿少2个缺口
64 actually. There are two missing.
# 64碗那就差不多跟以前
64 is what I expected
# 64碗
64 bowls
# 好啦 本期视频就到这里了 拜拜
Good. That's all for this episode. Bye bye.